<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plot to disseize God of his right defeated, and the contrivers punished discovered in a sermon preached in the Cathedral of S. Paul, on the 15th of September, 1661, before the Right Honorable Sir Richard Browne, Knight and Baronet, Lord Mayor of the city of London / by Tho. Wood ...</title>
            <author>Wood, Thomas, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66945</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3411</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9249</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12642606</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12642606</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65036</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66945)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65036)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 338:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plot to disseize God of his right defeated, and the contrivers punished discovered in a sermon preached in the Cathedral of S. Paul, on the 15th of September, 1661, before the Right Honorable Sir Richard Browne, Knight and Baronet, Lord Mayor of the city of London / by Tho. Wood ...</title>
                  <author>Wood, Thomas, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Godbid for R. Thrals ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Kings, 1st, I, 7 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65036:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65036:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PLOT To Diſſeize GOD of his RIGHT DEFEATED: <hi>AND</hi> The CONTRIVERS Puniſhed. <hi>DISCOVERED IN</hi> A SERMON Preached in the Cathedral of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> on the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>September,</hi> 1661. Before the Right Honorable Sir <hi>RICHARD BROWNE</hi> Knight and Baronet, Lord Mayor of the City of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By THO. WOOD, M. A.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Godbid</hi> for <hi>R. Thrale</hi> at the <hi>Croſs Keys</hi> at S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Gate entring into <hi>Cheapſide. M. DC. LXI.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:65036:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65036:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful The LADY <hi>LENNARD</hi> of <hi>Weſt-Wickham</hi> in <hi>Kent:</hi> and The LADY <hi>HARFLETE</hi> of S. <hi>Stephens</hi> neer <hi>Canterbury: Grace and Happineſs.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAMS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have obſerved in you both (which was partly a reaſon of joyning you together in this Dedication) a conſtant reſpect (in the worſt Times) towards the Old Clergy, when the firmament of our Church was ſadly and totally over-caſt, with Black Clouds of <hi>Novelliſme</hi> and <hi>Hereſie;</hi> even then your Aſpects were benigne and gracious, and rais'd the drooping ſpirits of the <hi>Orthodox Profeſſors</hi> round about you. I bleſs you for it, and God for you, who is faithful, and will moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly put it to your account at the general Day of Retribution.</p>
            <p>Particularly, I (the meaneſt in the Lords Vineyard, and ſave for my ſufferings) hardly conſiderable) have (in reference to my Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) receiv'd many Civilities from you, and muſt profeſs, that as I always honour'd you both, more for your goodneſs than your greatneſs, ſo I conceiv'd my ſelf oblig'd in
<pb facs="tcp:65036:3"/> gratitude to a publick acknowledgment, and wanting other means, have preſum'd upon this way. <hi>Madams,</hi> let it meet (I beſeech you) with a favourable interpretation. 'Tis a ſmall <hi>Peice,</hi> and was the fruit of my younger Studies. If the Style be ſomewhat Lofty, 'twas like my Thoughts when I compos'd it. Age and the Calamities of the Nation (in which I had a ſhare) have ſince broken and humbled mee. And 'tis impoſſible (without the wonder of a Miracle) I ſhould be made whole &amp; rais'd but by <hi>Diſſolution. Madams,</hi> I commend it to you onely as a Remembrancer, being able to add little to your Accompliſhments in matters of Information. It hath been preach'd in Three ſeveral great Aſſemblies, and (upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of ſome Friends) is, (ſuch as it is) ſent abroad into the world. I fear not much but 'twill indure the teſt, and meet with the ſame good liking in the Reading, which it had the happineſs to do in the reſpective Deliveries of it. It muſt needs paſs the more currant with all that know your Ladyſhips, if you deign: to ſtamp it with your acceptance and approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. I pray for you, and your Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipful Bedfellows. I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAMS,</salute> Your hearty Honorer and Servant in Chriſt Jeſus,
<signed>THO. WOOD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65036:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 Kings. 1. 7.</bibl>
               <q>And he took Counſel of <hi>Joab</hi> the ſon of <hi>Zer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viah,</hi> and of <hi>Abiathar</hi> the Prieſt, and they helped forward of <hi>Adonijah.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <argument>
               <p>My Deſign in the choice of this Scripture is to diſcover to this Honourable Corporation (and others of this great Aſſembly) <hi>A Plot.</hi> Not an imaginary one, ſuch as (for ends of State) you have had heretofore many obtruded upon you, but a real Plot. <hi>A Plot</hi> tending to no leſs then the Diſſeizing of the Lord <hi>Paramount</hi> of Heaven and Earth, God Almighty, of his right; withall, if the time will allow it, to manifeſt the <hi>Power</hi> of the ſame God in the <hi>Defeatment of it, and his Juſtice</hi> in the deſerved puniſhment upon the <hi>Delinquente</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have (not long ſince in a neighbour Aſſembly) entred upon this Argument, and by ſome (that are ſomewhat prevailing with me) am deſired to finiſh it here. The opening of the Story muſt not be omitted, for 'tis that which muſt give Light to every piece of the enſuing Diſcourſe; Several points will appear very intricate and dark in their Derivation without this. I deſire to make my way plain before me, and rather to run the hazzard of cenſure for ſomewhat a large repetition, then for <hi>Obſcurity.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N This Chapter we have two Brethren Competitors, ſcuffling hard which ſhall mount the firſt Chariot in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Either had read his thoughts ſuch a lofty Lecture, that like thoſe great Roman Cortivals, they can indure nor Superior nor Equal. A Kingdome is the prize they run for, they ſtrain the harder, as knowing he that loſeth, loſeth ſomething of Natures Priviledge, and muſt fall ſo much beneath a Brother, as (upon
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:65036:4"/> Humour or State-occaſion) to be reckon'd for no other then a Subject, a Servant. That which awakes them into action, and puts life into their Reſolutions, is the hourly expectation and Likelyhood of the long and laſt Sleep of their Father in Death. <hi>David,</hi> though a King, and ſo a God by his Office, yet by nature he was a man; and ſo, like the reſt of Mankind, muſt dye. His able Shoulders had for a good ſpace of time undergone their ſhare in the Burden of Government (as a ſubordinate Aſſiſtant) during the Reign of his Predeceſſor <hi>Saul,</hi> and for nere Forty years he had ſteer'd the Affairs of State in chief; ſo that now he was far gone into the ſecond Infancy of his Life, and could not conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue long, as having (at leaſt) one foot on the Threſhold of the Houſe appointed for all Living. This makes theſe two Brethren whom it only concern'd, the one by nature, the other by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, to bethink them early of their Intereſts: And becauſe in ſuch a weighty affair, bare right (by the ſecret judgement of God, and neglect of due afforded means for its ſupportation) doth ſometimes miſcarry, they underprop and fortifie it with the aſſociation of ſuch Friends, whoſe Power and Authority in the State, might almoſt without the juſtice of any Title, give credit and countenance to an adventurous Undertaker.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adonijah</hi> is the firſt that ſteps up the Stage to act his part, and he comes bravely on with Chariots and Horſe; and 50. Men to run before him. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 5. We may take a meaſure of him in the 6. <hi>Verſe,</hi> and that from three material Circumſtances, his Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Perſonage, and Birth; all (me-thinks) after a ſort pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy and foreſpeak what he intended, and ſeems to point him out not to a meaner Fortune then a Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The King, his Fathers Affection towards him was not to be doubted of; when <hi>David</hi> was a Man, and his Son a Child, he never diſpleaſed him, and 'twas not likely he would now go about to croſſe him, when himſelf was become Child, and his Son Man. He lov'd him but too well (as we have a Say.) His continual indulgent cockering Carriage toward him we find noted in the Text, and in probability not only as a peice of the Fathers Infirmity, but of the Sons Incouragement too. Something there was in it or elſe the Holy Ghoſt would never have left it upon record, that <hi>his Father would not diſpleaſe him from his Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, to ſay, Why haſt thou done ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:65036:4"/>
            <p>Secondly, Nature had plaid the Prodigal with him, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred on him much of her Bounty for his Body, <hi>He was a goodly man to look upon,</hi> ſaith the Text; and (if we'l credit the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of ſome Philoſophers) the parts of his Soul muſt then have been anſwerable. Indeed when we ſee a Houſe more then ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily beautified without, we are apt to imagine the furniture within to be more then ordinary too. Rich Caskets are commonly made to hold more precious Jewels; and ſet aſide divine Vertues (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Theives (as Flattery) ill Education, or the like, have robb'd Us of them) 'twill not (perhaps) be extremely abſurd to affirm the like of man. However comlineſſe of perſonage (it muſt be confeſt) as the Loadſtone doth Iron (by a ſecret yet irreſiſtible force) attracts our Love and Liking, and like a Conquerour inſlaves and captivates, compells our Affection. Had unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Abſolon</hi> been this way unbefriended, I make a Queſtion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all his other Court Policies in wrigling, and inſinuating him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into the favour of the People, had ever gaim'd ſo much upon them, as to have rais'd them in ſuch multitudes to ſide with him againſt their Soveraign? <hi>Adonijah</hi> his Brother here hath the very ſame advantage, that which would have exceedingly much ſet off a private man, but a Prince as he was, more: as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving from other Complements of ſuch greatneſſe a reciprocal addition of Luſtre.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, But there's another thing behind, which ſeems to be more available to his Ends then both theſe, and 'tis laid down in the words immediately preceeding the Text; <hi>His Mother bare him,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>His Mother bare him next after Abſolon?</hi> Why, what's that to the purpoſe? How comes this any way to advantage and promote his Cauſe? Yes, very much. <hi>Ammon</hi> the eldeſt Son (as we may read) was divers years before ſlain by <hi>Abſolon;</hi> And <hi>Abſolon</hi> the ſecond Son again ſlain by <hi>Joab;</hi> and ſo as if they had never been, the natural right is devolv'd, and reſts upon the next Surviver. If <hi>Ammon</hi> or <hi>Abſolon</hi> were the eldeſt whilſt they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>Adonijah</hi> is ſo now they are dead. So that we ſee here that he hath the Priviledge of <hi>Primogeniture,</hi> and that alwayes (as we have a Proverb) carries <hi>Meat in the Mouth of it.</hi> By the very Law of God a double portion was due to it, and becauſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes admit not of Diviſion, of Partition (in thoſe that are
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65036:5"/> ſettled in a Succeſſion) by the Law of God, of Nations, to the whole.</p>
            <p>So that you ſee he hath Three ſtrings to his Bowe, a threefold Cord to ſtrengthen and aſſure his hopes, and that (his wiſe bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tells us) is not eaſily broken.</p>
            <p>But though his Tackling were thus good, yet like a diſcreet man he warily ſuſpects and provides for a greater Tempeſt then was likely to happen. His Competitor was a youth, nay very little more then a Child: and ſuch (we know) men deſire not ſhould Reign over them; a Child too of a Mother tainted formerly with the Stain of known Adultery; and that, queſtionleſſe, bated him ſomething too in the common opinion. And yet our Pretender is as careful to ſettle and aſſure his cauſe, as if his Corrival had been a well-grown man like himſelf, and had had too the ſtart of him in reputation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In weighty Affairs 'tis ſtill the wiſeſt and ſafeſt courſe to doubt the worſt; to forecaſt the Extremity, and to prevent and provide for that. How many have loſt an Inheritance, a Lordſhip, a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, nay</hi> (by ſomes leave) <hi>Heaven it ſelf by reckoning them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves but too ſure on't.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adonijah</hi> here, was a man of another Temper: He hath a fair Game we ſee, which doth in a manner aſſure him the Stake, yet for all this like a wary adventurer, he remits nothing of his care, but playes it with all advice and deliberation poſſible: So in the Text, <hi>And he took Counſell, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words we may conſider the two parts of all great Enterpriſes; 1. <hi>Conſultation. 2. Action.</hi> And this in hand being of that nature, we have of either a plain Deſcription.</p>
            <p>Firſt, we have three plotting heads laid together, and ſo taken; (though one but young) perhaps not Three wiſer between <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Beerſheba.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, We have three pair of hands executing the contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of theſe heads.</p>
            <p>For from either we muſt not exclude him whom it all concerns. The firſt word (<hi>He</hi>) makes him a Party in the Conſultation; The laſt word (<hi>Adonijah</hi>) makes him ſo in the <hi>Action.</hi> His ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice undoubtedly was not wanting in his own cauſe, nor ſtood he then by as an idle Spectatour, but as they helped him forward, ſo he too help'd forward himſelf.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:65036:5"/>
            <p>The end, reaſon, and But which they drive at in both, is to make this younger head, <hi>Head</hi> both of Young and Old in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> To ſet him upon the Throne of his Father, and publickly in the face of the World to juſtifie his private-taken-up-reſolution. <hi>I will be King, verſ.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>This was their aim about this they conſult.</p>
            <p>I might here (for the firſt part of my Text) enter upon a Common place of <hi>Counſell.</hi> Be plentiful in Quotations of what divine and prophane Writers, Oratours, Hiſtorians, Poets, have delivered in commendation of it.</p>
            <p>I might too enlarge the praiſes of it from experience generally how 'tis of ſingular uſe, nay abſolute neceſſity to the well mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of all weighty concerning Affairs, particularly in matters of Government; how 'tis the Steerſman of a State, the Soul of all Sound Policy, and that which (next under Heaven) a Kingdome may chiefly thank for all its Happineſſe, Peace, Plenty, every good thing. If in matters of War, how by it ſmall things have confounded great; Ten men ſhut up a Thouſand, an handful over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown a Million. Amplified likewiſe further it might be from its contrary; What frequent examples there are in all Story of manifeſt and miſerable inconveniencies, which men of all forts have run themſelves into by inconſiderate raſhneſſe and temera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious precipitation.</p>
            <p>Again (from the ſecond part of my Text) I might go on upon another head of Action, tell you, that 'tis this which renders Conſultations, Illuſtrious; Counſells are dark things, begot in obſcurity, and ſo nouriſhed, and ordinarily ſhew not themſelves to the World but by this. Indeed they are but Illuſions, when Action is not deſign'd to back them. And as faith without works is but an abuſive <hi>miſleading Chymaera,</hi> ſo 'tis here; Though Counſel ſeem to conſiſt of more ſpiritual parts then Action, yet 'tis Action that makes the <hi>Demonſtration;</hi> that raiſes out of the duſt and gives Life and a Laſting Luſtre to thoſe <hi>advices,</hi> which elſe had periſhed like the untimely fruit of a Woman, and had never ſeen the Sun. This and more (upon theſe two heads) might be largely diſcours'd on, and the Text doth ſeem to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant it; but I ſhall take Leave to leave theſe general Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and to fall up more cloſely, with the particularities of the Story.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:65036:6"/>
            <p>In this Chapter then (as I told you, for ſubſtance in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) we have a Kingdome at Stake, and Two Brethren Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters playing hard for it. The elder and more experienc'd, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, yet perhaps we cannot ſay 'twas ſo much his fault as his <hi>destiny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He had Heaven againſt him, or elſe we might juſtly wonder he came not off the Winner: for, for his <hi>Title</hi> and <hi>Likelyhoods</hi> we have them in the precedent Verſe, and in this the well managing of both, <hi>He took Counſell, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where firſt (to make way to my after Diſcourſe) give me leave to obſerve that his ambition was better order'd and tutor'd then his Brother <hi>Abſolons.</hi> I find not that he did any way <hi>envy</hi> or <hi>undermine</hi> his Fathers <hi>honour,</hi> or that he did ſo much as in a wiſh deſire his Death. Let this be his <hi>Piety,</hi> ſith Slighter hopes have made ſome Children ſo ſtrangely unnatural as to do more to effect it. No ſuch black thoughts came nere the Soul of our <hi>Adonijah,</hi> his ends and aims (for ought appears evidently from the Text) were more fair and juſtifiable; Not like his Brother to <hi>un-King</hi> his Father, but to reign after him; not to <hi>depoſe</hi> but to <hi>ſucceed</hi> him, was the ſumme of his Intentions; and who can blame an eldeſt Son for this? Make his caſe but your own, and (I believe) he'll be like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enough to go away not only not openly rebuked, but ſecretly incouraged; eſpecially when he takes no groſly indirect, nay a ſeemingly fair and lawful courſe to compaſſe it. Confers his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign too with thoſe, who had it been <hi>unlawful</hi> ſhould have dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted him, his Ghoſtly Father <hi>Abiathar,</hi> and his experienc'd Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin <hi>Joab.</hi> But theſe are as forward as he, and not only adviſe him, but afford their helping hands likewiſe in the buſineſſe; <hi>They hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped forward Anonijah, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I ſhall deal with <hi>them</hi> in an after Diſcourſe, give me leave firſt to diſpatch the worthier perſon.</p>
            <p>And in him ſecondly, in every paſſage of the Text (conſidering the Affair in hand) I obſerve abundance of Wiſdome and ſound Policy.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That he does not go raſhly to work, but takes <hi>Counſell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, That he takes Counſel of ſuch as were able to give it, and whoſe Countenance too, was as available as their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel. <hi>And he took Counſel of Joab, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:65036:6"/>
            <p>That he doth impart theſe important privacies to ſuch, whom formerly he had ſo firmly aſſur'd to himſelf, as to run the haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of their own Counſells, and really to engage themſelves in it by Action. What they adviſe they do, <hi>They helped, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, He goes not headdily and raſhly to work, but <hi>Takes Counſell;</hi> The Wiſe man ſaith, <hi>There's more hope of a Fool then of a man haſty in matters, Prov.</hi> 29, 20. And (if I remember right) <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> I have read, taxed for this kind of Folly, of whom ſomebody records, that he ſeldome asked, never followed the advice of others. To be ſo overwiſe in our own Conceits, as to deſpiſe or neglect the Counſell of our Friends, is a ſtrong Argument of weakneſſe, and hears ill among the very Heathen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Agamemnon</hi> (a wiſe Prince) wiſheth (in <hi>Homer</hi>) that he had Ten <hi>Neſtors</hi> to conſult withall; and a wiſer then he tells us, that <hi>in the multitude of Counſellors there is Safety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed, however we find in Story ſome few ſuddain Actions to have ſucceeded well, yet their Glory is ſtill blemiſh'd with the ſtain of raſhneſſe, and blind <hi>Fortune,</hi> more entituled to them then the undertakers. We have a Proverb amongſt us ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to this purpoſe; <hi>'Tis more by hap, then any good Cunning.</hi> We cannot faſten this fault upon our <hi>Adonijah,</hi> he was no haſty inconſiderate <hi>Hotſpurre;</hi> did not precipitate himſelf headlong into the buſineſſe, <hi>fall back, fall edge,</hi> (as we have a word) but he looks before he <hi>leaps,</hi> chooſeth his beſt ground for riſing, goes on with wary advice and ſound Deliberation. 'Tis the firſt point of his Wiſdome, and in it I commend him as a Pattern for your Imitation, <hi>In all weighty Affairs do as he did, Take Counſell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſecondly, ſome have judgement enough, to ſee into their own want of judgement, yet too little to make a fit Election of ſuch as may inform them. They can perceive Counſell to be good, and in divers caſes themſelves to ſtand in need of it, yet have not attain'd to that happy height of Wiſdome, to ſelect and ſingle out ſuch as are beſt able to give it. <hi>Rehoboam</hi> nephew to our <hi>Adonijah,</hi> was one of this number; who refuſed to be gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by experience and gray hairs, but embraceth the raw and green advice of ſuch as were like himſelf; and we may read it coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65036:7"/> dear, the revolt of ten Tribes, five parts in ſix of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>So was <hi>Antiochus</hi> the great too, in his war againſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> and <hi>Zerxes</hi> a greater then he, in his expedition into <hi>Graecia,</hi> both weakly followed the feeble counſel of their effeminate Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, men utterly unacquainted with Martial Diſcipline and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, ſave ſuperficially to diſcourſe on't, before the ſtrong advice of thoſe tried ſpirits, the exiled <hi>Hero's,</hi> and that ever renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, though unfortunate <hi>Hannibal.</hi> And they find the ſucceſs an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable. The one at length, (in the midſt of his own ſtrength) is baſely brav'd by but a Miniſter of State, imperiouſly circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by an imaginary circle drawn with a wand about him, and is fain unworthily to ſtoop and take law from his Inferiour. The other after the loſs of divers thouſands of lives, glad to eſcape in a ſmall Veſſel, and by the ill carriage of the action, diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſo much of the weakneſs of the <hi>Aſiatiques</hi> his ſubjects, as gave courage to his enemies in the next Age to invade and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the whole <hi>Perſian</hi> Empire.</p>
            <p>And from ſuch like obſervations ſome have drawn this ſafe rule in Polity, and it holds in Reaſon, and in Religion too. <hi>In a doubtful caſe rather to incline to the advice of ſuch as have been vers'd in the buſineſs enquired after. Thus in matters of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to give ear to the Stateſman; in matters of War, to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by the Souldier; and in things pertaining to our ſouls and ſalvations. not to be led aſide by every new <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pſtart, every private Fanatique ſpirit, but to be guided by the Church-man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet it muſt be confeſt this rule holds not generally, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it miſcarries, and yet when it doth, it carries a fair excuſe along with it; <hi>That man can never be tax'd of much, of groſs weakneſs, (unleſs he before-hand know men to be perſidious) that believes them in their particular profeſſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this rule though good, yet is not full. Other conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions muſt be taken in too, (which I make no queſtion <hi>Adonijah</hi> had a reſpect to) and they likewiſe according to the quality of the perſons, vary exceedingly.</p>
            <p>Private men when they conſult of their particular intereſts, may take courſes of their own. The narrowneſs of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal conditions and relations afford them more liberty, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65036:7"/> their errours are neither ſo material nor diſcernable.</p>
            <p>But matters of State, publick Buſineſs of Kingdomes, tying us to a kind of formality, muſt be carried in a Majeſtique way of diſcuſſion, and are not to want any complemental circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, which at home may render them leſs venerable, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad diminiſh their reputation. And ſo a care is to be had that the men be both great and good, whoſe advice we follow. Great, to prevent envy and contempt; Good, (in account at leaſt) to avoid ſcandal and diſcredit.</p>
            <p>If the perſon that gives counſel be mean, though he ſpeak like an Oracle, 'twill be ſlighted; nay, cavilled at. The Wiſe man obſerved ſome ſuch thing in his time, when he tells, <hi>If a rich man ſpake, the people kept ſilence, but if poor, they were ready to ſtop his mouth with that courſe quaere, What fellow's this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, though the men be great, if they be not good too, their advice though as good as <hi>Achitophel</hi>'s, will be liable to prejudice. Hence (if I rightly record) the <hi>Lacedemonian Senators</hi> were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding coy of their Suffrages to a very profitable propoſition for their Republick, laid before them by a lewd great one; yet under-hand cauſed the very ſame thing to be propounded by one of more upright converſation, and it paſs'd the Houſe with great applauſe.</p>
            <p>I might be long in this Argument, but muſt call home.</p>
            <p>I find out <hi>Adonijah</hi>'s wiſdome approvable in this particular too; He communicates not his deſign with inexperienc'd <hi>Young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> men either of looſe Titles, or leud Conditions; but with ſuch as were of conſpicuous eminency, acquainted with the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bowels and ſecrets of the <hi>State,</hi> and that knew better then any how to ſteer him in his deſired courſe. Of ſuch authority and reputation too by reaſon of their places and perſons, exceedingly countenance the action, and draw multitudes of their dependants and others, either out of <hi>fear, love,</hi> or <hi>opinion,</hi> to declare themſelves for him, or to ſtagger at leaſt, and ſtand as <hi>Neuters.</hi> The <hi>invincible Joab,</hi> and the <hi>High Prieſt Abiathar,</hi> theſe conſult and adviſe with him; nay, they do more, <hi>they help him forward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this Thirdly, Manifeſts yet ſomething more our young <hi>Princes</hi> wiſdome too. Many will give good counſel, not out
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65036:8"/> of any love to the perſon or cauſe, but to ſcrew themſelves into truſt, that ſo upon occaſion they may the more certainly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw both. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon ſuſpitious men</hi> (therefore) <hi>though they ſpeak well, we are never to lean ſo hard as (ſhould they treacherouſly ſlip aſide) to give out ſelves a fall. Abſolon</hi> was ſomewhat this way indiſcreet, in ſo ſuddenly embracing the advice of <hi>Hn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhai</hi> the <hi>Atchite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, Some will give counſel, yea, and ſincerely too; but if in a buſineſs that imports danger, they deſire not to be ſeen in it. You have not ſuch great intereſt in them, not ſo far enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them to you, as to cauſe them to do more then barely to adviſe, when perhaps their countenance were as good as their counſel, and would themſelves aſſiſt in the execution, 'twere yet like to ſucceed much better. For I think I need not ask leave to think, That <hi>ſuch as can ſoundly adviſe (if they be ſincere in the buſineſs, and alike in other things) are moſt fit to excoute, as knowing beſt the extent, breadth, depth and length of their own counſels, and able too at home, to furniſh themſelves afreſh, upon the accidental miſcarriage of any particular.</hi> I muſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber home again.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Adonijah</hi>'s wiſdome is herein remarkable too, that ſuch as he doth communicate his deſign withal, he had before by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, obſervance, and other ways of courteſie and inſinuation, ſo firmly aſſured to himſelf, as firſt, to deal ſincerely with him, more to declare themſelves for him, moſt of all to run the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of their own counſel, and really to engage themſelves in it by <hi>action.</hi> We find it in the laſt words, <hi>They helped forward,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>To ſum up all together, and ſo to make way to the main Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</p>
            <p>We have here an able young man, laying a ſtrong foundation of greatneſs, encouraged to it by the King, his Fathers Love, and that double bounty of nature, comelineſs of perſonage, and el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſhip; aſſiſted in it by thoſe of greateſt power and ſway in the State, <hi>Abiathar the high Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>Joab Captain of the Hoſt,</hi> who delude him not with <hi>Court-Holy-Water,</hi> (a piece of falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, a meer ſtranger for the moſt part to true Prieſts and right Souldiers) but their works ſpeak them as good as their words; they afford him head, and hands, and hearts too in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65036:8"/> 
               <hi>They adviſe him, they help him forward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And he that ſhall conſideratively read thus far the ſtory, (ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of what enſured afterwards) would willingly (I ſuppoſe) venture his fortune in the ſame Bottome with the undertake For the deſign in the whole managing of it diſcovers ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> apparencies and probabilities of ſucceſs, as indeed 'tis a matter of juſt marvel to think how it did miſcarry. But here we ſee <hi>Heavens Power and Prerogative, how it eaſily alters and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throws Projects that ſeem to be founded and rooted in Adamant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord doth whatever he will both in Heaven and Earth, and, ſhould the whole world conſpire in an inſurrection to revenſe or alter one of his leaſt decrees, their attempts would prove as vain as ridiculous. <hi>For he that dwells in Heaven would laugh them to ſcorn, the Lord would have them in deriſion, Pſalm</hi> 2. 3. A remarkable place to this purpoſe is that in the Prophecy of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaiah, chap. 3. ver.</hi> 9, 10, 11. Where we find a confederacy, an aſſociation of divers perſons, nay, in likelihood Nations too, againſt the people of God. Like that combination mentioned by the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal. 83. 6, 7, 8. Gebal, Ammon, Amalek.</hi> the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> with the <hi>Tyrians, Aſſur,</hi> and the children of <hi>Lot, Edomites, Iſhmaclites, Moabites, Hagarens,</hi> men of divers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, and not all of one and the ſame Religion neither, though all aliens to the Common-wealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſtrangers to the Covenant, or like (to come ſo neer, and no neerer) that holy League in <hi>France,</hi> the cauſe of ſo much miſchief to that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, (and by their example to others.) Well, but (for proof of the main Obſervation) mark what God ſaith there by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>Aſſociate your ſelves together, and ye ſhall be broken to pieces; Gird your ſelves,</hi> (put your ſelves into a poſture of war) broken to pieces notwithſtanding. This judgment (<hi>of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing broken to pieces</hi>) we find thrice repeated in that ninth verſe, to note the fulneſs, centainty, and in Gods time, ſuddenneſs of ſuch contrivers deſtruction; and though they all lay their heads together to prevent it, yet it will not do. <hi>Take counſel toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> (ver. 10.) <hi>it ſhall be brought to nought, make a decnee, it ſhall not ſtand;</hi> and the Prophet ſhews his extraordinary Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for this in the eleventh verſe. <hi>The Lord ſpake this to me with a high hand.</hi> And it is juſt the ſame with the example
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65036:9"/> in the Text. They take counſel here for <hi>Adonijah</hi>'s ſucceſſion, but God (as the <hi>Pſalmist</hi> ſpeaks) breaks this counſel, and brings to nought this device. He hath ſaid, <hi>Solomon ſhall reign,</hi> and he will not alter the thing that is gone forth of his lips; Though all the <hi>Achitophels</hi> and <hi>Statists</hi> upon Earth project the contrary, yet his counſel ſhall <hi>for ever, and the thoughts of his heart from generation to generation,</hi> Pſalm 33. 11. Wiſdome and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and counſel do bravely bring to paſs mighty matters, ſo long as they keep their diſtance, but when once they'll dare <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omakiſme,</hi> and <hi>Giant</hi>-like wage war againſt Heaven, then they turn to fooliſhneſs. He tells us ſo that had experience of it, (as in divers other paſſages, ſo in this particular of the Text) <hi>There is neither wiſdome, nor underſtanding, nor counſel againſt the Lord,</hi> Prov. 21. 30.</p>
            <p>To reduce this meditation into matter of Uſe and Practice.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It ſerves for Caution. And the advice in brief will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to thus much. That we are to take heed as how we fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a multitude: So how we ſide with a few eminent men in any evil deſign. The Kingdome of <hi>Iſrael</hi> (by what we find evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently recorded) was at this time miſerably divided; and it was Gods extraordinary mercy towards them, that it broke not forth into the greateſt of plagues and miſchiefs, <hi>A Civil War:</hi> Read through this only Chapter, and but conſideratively weigh what is written, and you'll apprehend as much as I have inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated. Here was at one ſide the renowned <hi>Joab, Generaliſſimo</hi> of the Hoſts of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> one who had merited that honour by a remarkable act of valour at his entrance, and ſince for neer for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years had managed it with ſuch ſucceſs, that who could ſay, <hi>Joab</hi> ever turned his back upon his enemy? nay, that his ſword ever was ſheathed undrunken with the blood of the ſlain? Here went along with him all the Captains of the Hoſt, and it may be preſumed (though unmentioned) that far the major part of the ſouldiers followed their Leaders. Beſides, as fair additionals, (not only for ſhew, but uſe too) here were all the Blood-Royal, and all the Kings ſervants that ſwam with this Current, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barqued themſelves in the buſineſs; and which was almoſt as much as all, here was the high Prieſt, head of the <hi>Church in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cris,</hi> who had walked <hi>ſo many years</hi> in and out before the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:65036:9"/> unblameably, and by whoſe deciſion and definitive ſentence moſt caſes of conſciences were <hi>de jure,</hi> determinable; and que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſs moſt of the inferiour Prieſts by his command, or (at leaſt) the authority of his example, put their hands to this work, and by inſiſting on that Text about the <hi>firſt-born</hi> in their <hi>Haran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues</hi> and diſcourſes to the people, boldly bore them in hand, that it was the cauſe of God, the will of Heaven which they plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, there wanted not a Prophet <hi>Nathan,</hi> and a very eminent Prieſt too, chief of thoſe about the Tabernacle, <hi>Zadok;</hi> and both theſe had undoubtedly their followers, which did as much for <hi>Solomon.</hi> Here were beſides <hi>Benaijah</hi> one of the chief of <hi>David</hi>'s Worthies, together with <hi>Shimei</hi> and <hi>Rei,</hi> perſons very remarkable. The <hi>Cherethites,</hi> and <hi>Pelethites</hi> pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed choice men of eminent ſtature and courage, exempted from <hi>Joabs</hi> juriſdiction, and appointed under the foreſaid famous <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naijah,</hi> for the guard of the Kings body.</p>
            <p>So that here we find Stateſman againſt Stateſman, Captain againſt Captain, Souldier againſt Souldier, and (which common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puzzles the general ſort of people moſt) <hi>Altare contra Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare,</hi> a Prophet joyn'd with a chief Prieſt to ballance <hi>Abiathar</hi> the Supreme; And the diviſion (I make no queſtion) went proportionably downward to the very skirts of <hi>Aarons</hi> order. And though the advantage (had the quarrel been ſuddenly to have been comprimis'd by the ſwords deciſion) lay clearly in all humane probability on the ſide of <hi>Adonijah.</hi> Yet knowing upright men meaſure not their adherence to a cauſe ſo much by the rule of power as juſtice; and the inferiour multitude who wanted the ſpirit of diſcerning, and in ſuch bickerings were <hi>ſure</hi> to carry away the moſt blows, could not but be exceedingly ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered and diſtracted, to obſerve the ſtrange ſidings amongſt the powerful, the prudent, and the reputed religious, which ſate next the Helm of the State. (In all difficulties undeterminable at home) their opinion of others whom they fancy honeſt and wiſer then themſelves, being almoſt the only Pole-ſtar they ſteer their courſe by.</p>
            <p>We have drawn a picture of <hi>Iſraels</hi> condition, and (it was within theſe few years) ſo like our own, that it may ſave the art
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65036:10"/> of a farther Pencil, and changing but the names, ſerve as well for <hi>England.</hi> For though with us there were not two ſeveral Pretenders to the Supreme Title, yet (which doth <hi>tantamount</hi>) to the Supreme Power, there were manifeſtly; and the caſe in the Text of elder and younger, Nature and Promiſe, was not neither (if we look to the bottome of the buſineſs) a ſtranger to our Controverſie.</p>
            <p>What God in mercy prevented amongſt them, he hath in judgment (the fury of his indignation) permitted to fall upon us. We have had the miſerable experience of a ſad, miſerable Civil War, and that accompanyed with as much diviſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween men of all ſorts, degrees and conditions, and proſecuted with as much Heatheniſh heart-burning, as (I believe) ſince there were men enough in the world to make up ſuch a politique Society as a Kingdome, never more in any. And becauſe Civil ſtrifes are never ſo hotly purſued as Religious, coldneſs (which in other contentions is preſumed to proceed from modemtion) being not admitted the favour of ſuch a conſtruction in this, (to exaſperate mens minds more) This War was at firſt (by the cunning of ſome) ſo Chriſtians and the Laws of the Land, the Liberty of the Subject, and I know not what other Priviledges, brought in as Goſipps yea, and the Solemnity and Sacrament of an Oath likewiſe added, to terrifie back-ſliders, diſcover ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and aſſociate friends more firmly. Well, we fought, and who would have thought that the noiſe (though once we find in the caſe of the barbarous <hi>Midianites,</hi> Judg. 7. 12.) of a few empty Pitchers, and ſome fiery Lights, could have engaged a peaceable and wiſe people againſt one another ſo felly, ſo foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly. I need not acquaint you with the ſucceſs. He is a ſtrauge ſtranger in our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that knows not what hath rome to paſs in our daies. A Succeſs (I confeſs) ſo extraordinary unexpected, ſudden and compleat, as would have ſtaggered any faith, not built upon a rock; ſet off any Cauſe (if but tolerably hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome) even to an envious degree of beauty and glory; yet (by the ſecret judgment of God) it contributed ſo little to this, that the prevailing party never found themſelves at ſo great a loſs, as when they had gained all; never felt themſelves ſo weak, as when there was not an enemy to ſtand before them.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65036:10"/> For falling now upon the diviſion of the ſpoil, not without vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible diſagreement, (confident likewiſe to draw the Curtain, and diſcover the great Deſign) there did follow ſuch a general alienation of affections, ſuch an averſion from what people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo exceedingly over-much doted upon, that a Parallel to it can hardly be re-mark'd in any ſtory, and which (by the merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſpoſition of God Almighty) hath produced the happineſs which (for above fifteen moneths) we have ſeen and felt.</p>
            <p>To conclude this firſt Uſe of Caution. To you of this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable City.</p>
            <p>Let us from henceforth take heed how we be carried about with every wind of doctrine, or every blaſt of preſent Succeſs, that we believe not every ſpirit, or powerful perſwaſion, or great example, for divers that boaſt themſelves of God are not ſuch; many falſe Prophets are come forth into the world.</p>
            <p>Let it be enough, that by glorious glittering pretences we have been cheated out of our <hi>Religion, Loyalty,</hi> Property; nay our very Reaſon, that by ſtrong <hi>dazeling deluſions,</hi> we have been <hi>cajol'd</hi> iuto ſuch a Pit-fall, from which only the Almighty power and extraordinary Goodneſſe could, redeem us. If our own harms will not make us beware, neither the Texts Example, nor any humane Inſtruction can poſſibly work upon us. And the next blow of Gods hand muſt needs be far heavier, becauſe we have ſo ſoon forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the grief of our former miſery, and the comfort of our preſent Deliverance.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for <hi>Comfort.</hi> To ſtay our hearts as with Flagons of Wine, when we conſider, that not one word of Heavens mouth, made to our own ſouls or others, ſhall fall to the Ground. Is thy faith aſſaulted concerning the truth of Gods promiſes, made either to the whole Church, as the Body in the general; or to thy ſelf, as a Member in particular.</p>
            <p>Take heed of giving too far and free Entertainment to ſuch Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions The Lords hand is not ſhortned, He's commonly bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then his word, as good as his word (to be ſure) he is always. Though, for the preſent, perhaps thou mayeſt perceive nothing leſſe, no Shadow of Likelyhood, all thing to run to a Retro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:65036:11"/> courſe to their ſeeming accompliſhment. Yet poſſeſſe thy Soul with patience, ſtand and ſee the Salvation of the Lord, reſt upon his All-ſufficiency, believe with <hi>Abraham,</hi> even above hope, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He doth divers times work out his ends by means, in our ſhallow conceits apparently contrary. He's ſo good that he would not ſuffer evill to be, unleſſe he were alſo ſo powerful as to be able to draw good out of it. Nothing can make void the purpoſes and promiſes of Heaven. Though a <hi>Joab,</hi> though an <hi>Abiathar,</hi> though all men on Earth, and Divels in Hell, attempt their Nullity: yet Maugre all Oppoſition, they ſhall ſtand in force, and be made good to thoſe whom they concern; that Word of truth hath ſpoken it, not one word of whoſe Truth, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn empty, <hi>Heaven and Earth ſhall paſſe away, but, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Third, for <hi>Direction,</hi> to ſteer our courſe on the troubleſome Sea of this World, that ſo we may arrive at the Haven where we would be; and that is in all our Intendments to take Heaven along with us, not to depend upon new Truths, pretended to be concealed for ſo many Generations, and now revealed to I know not whom, for I know not what <hi>fanciful purpoſes,</hi> but to make Gods clear revealed Word (with <hi>David</hi>) our Counſellor, and Warrant, and then we ſhall be ſure to have either the Summe of our Deſires, or that which is better for us. Then either our purpoſes ſhall have a good Iſſue, or elſe our failing in them ſhall be more for our Good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Inſtance:</hi> You of this City, deſire to be rich, and in places of Honour and Eminency, and ſuch deſires (if attended with their due Qualifications) are for ought I know not amiſſe neither. Now <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, that riches and honour are in the hands of the Almighty: <hi>Length of Dayes are in his right hand, and in his left Riches and Honour. Prov.</hi> And if we'l credit the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel he'l tell us that all theſe are his too, once to be ſure we know he told the very Owner ſo to his Face, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4. and where he is likely to gain more belief, he will cettainly be more forward to boaſt his vain Title. And were there not too many in the World that lent a willing ear to him; the forbidden paths of Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, Flattery, Extortion, Over-reaching, Cozenage, and Cunning; would not be ſo crowded with Paſſengers, and the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable Road of Truth and Honeſty, fair upright, and ingenious Dealing, ſo thinly frequented.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:65036:11"/>
            <p>But brag the Divel never ſo confidently, of theſe and all other good things, God is the true <hi>Proprietary;</hi> and we muſt have and hold them of him, if we will have and hold them at all, or long, or with Comfort. We take an ill Match in hand if we go about to wreſtle with him, and wreſt them from him by Violence. God is a liberal God, and yet in ſome Senſe he's a hand-faſt God too; maugre all the World, he can keep his hands ſhut if he pleaſe, and untill he be pleaſed to open it, we cannot be filled with Plenteouſneſſe. In all our Enterpriſes therefore, let us be ſure to have him to friend, to have his allowance at leaſt, if not command, in the main Intendments of our Life, otherwiſe (let me tell you) 'tis neither the Plotting of our heads, nor the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitouſneſſe of our hearts, not the Drudgery of our hands, nor the whole concurrence of our created ſtrength, improv'd by all acceſſory procurable Aſſiſtances, that can finally render our at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts ſucceſſeful. <hi>Adam</hi> may make himſelf a Garment, but it ſhall not cover his nakedneſs; <hi>Jonah</hi> may build him a booth, but it ſhall not defend him from the heat of the Sun; <hi>Peter</hi> may toil all right at fiſhing, but ſhall catch nothing. <hi>Though we riſe up early, and lie down late, and eat the bread of ſorrow, yet is our labour in vain, except the Lord give the bleſſing,</hi> Pſalm 127. 2.</p>
            <p>I might illuſtrate this by almoſt infinite inſtances out of Story. Take the Texts example for all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Here is an able eldeſt Son uſing the ſtrongeſt humane means to ſettle himſelf in the Seat of his Father: Ordering this affair with as much polity and diſcretion, as the beſt heads in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome could furniſh him with. Many advantages he had of his Competitor, both the</hi> Word <hi>and the</hi> Sword (if I may ſo ſpeak) <hi>were on his ſide. The High Prieſt and Captain of the Hoſt: The latter of which alone was ſo powerful in the State, that</hi> David <hi>himſelf (though a King well-beloved of his Subjects) confeſſeth him too hard for him, and for the murder of divers of his dear friends, durſt not puniſh him. Yet ſee notwithſtanding all theſe intereſts, aſſiſtances, probabilities, Heaven overſwaies and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines the contrary: Go but to the latter end of the Chapter, and there we ſhall read that</hi> Solomon <hi>is King. So true is that of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65036:12"/> the holy Ghost, the fooliſhneſs of God is wiſer then mans wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and his weakneſs ſtronger then their power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſtay; was indeed God's hand in this buſineſs againſt <hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nijah?</hi> How then durſt either <hi>Joab</hi> or <hi>Abiathar</hi> move ſo much as a finger for him? Nay, how durſt he himſelf take counſel and plead his own Title, when that Wonderful Counſellour and Supreme Judge both of Heaven and Earth was in the Cauſe his adverſary?</p>
            <p>1. But indeed for him, firſt, I can eaſily ſatisfie my ſelf without the puzzle of a wonderment. A Crown is a ſtrong temptation, and where an apprehenſion of compaſſing it gets footing in the brain, it infatuates, corrupts our judgments, and inveigles us to any impious, deſperate undertaking. <hi>Caeſar,</hi> thought a Kingdome worth an oath-breaking. And I have obſerved it, that Religion hath not ſuch another ſhrewd enemy as ambition. Look into the Annals of all ages, ſearch the Records of time from the beginning, and you'll ſcarce find one of a thouſand that have let go their hold, or relinquiſh'd probabilities of Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, out of a meer reſpect to conſcience.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For <hi>Joab</hi> too, I marvel not at all at him. A man he was it ſeems by the whole courſe and tenour of his actions, of a violent, over-heady ſpirit. One that look'd no farther (though a Subject, and an <hi>Iſraelite</hi>) for a Law, then his own will. He had ſlain <hi>Abſolon</hi> expreſly againſt the King's Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, and <hi>Abner</hi> and <hi>Amaſa</hi> againſt both Gods and the Kings; And if he now beard Heaven by oppoſing with a high hand its decrees, which had ſo often before ſet nought and ſlight by it, what need we wonder.</p>
            <p>But for <hi>Abiathar</hi> me-thinks to do ſo, cannot but rouze our admiration: For God's high Prieſt to ſet himſelf againſt God, and to oppoſe his will and purpoſes, muſt needs be to thoſe that conſider the circumſtances of the ſtory and perſon, a matter of juſt aſtoniſhment. Shall we ſay for him by way of excuſe, or extenuation, that perchance he might not be clearly and through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:65036:12"/> acquainted with God's will in this particular. We would fain be as favourable to him as might be, but this in reaſon allow him we cannot. For then (unleſs we'll argue like <hi>Turks) Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſpoke amiſs to him, <hi>chap.</hi> 2. 26. When he told him he had deſerved death; for ſuppoſing him ignorant do but ſhew me what ſo great evil he had done.</p>
            <p>But indeed faulty he was, I make no queſtion, knowingly and preſumptuouſly faulty too. God had ſent the Prophet <hi>Nathan</hi> to beſtow a ſecond name upon <hi>Solomon,</hi> a name of ſuch an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſignification, as might almoſt alone direct <hi>Abiathar</hi> to the Almighty's intention, <hi>Jedidiah</hi> the beloved of the Lord. And that ſome clearer intimation of God's pleaſure was the ground of <hi>Davids</hi> oath to <hi>Bathſheba</hi> by the Lord, that her ſon ſhould reign after him, may be more then probably conjectured. For can we ſuppoſe that <hi>David</hi> a Prophet of the Lord, would ſo reſolutely (without limitation, or Saint <hi>James</hi> his reſervation, <hi>if the Lord will</hi>) ſwear, that <hi>Solomon</hi> ſhould reign after him, without a Warrant from him by whom Kings reign, and the Thrones of Princes are eſtabliſhed. And that this being ſuch a publick buſineſs, and neceſſary to be known too, ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed from <hi>Abiathar,</hi> no circumſtances can make likely. I take no pleaſure in this Argument; Give me leave from hence only to note unto you, That the beſt ſometimes over-ſhoot themſelves groſly; That not a Miter, not an Ephod, not the holy Calling of Prieſthood, doth make us ſo univerſally good, but that we ſometimes run into a <hi>Premunire</hi> againſt Heaven, tranſgreſs the Laws of our Maker like other men. We are earthly Veſſels, kneaded of the ſame Clay, ſhap'd of the ſame mould whereof all mankind are faſhioned. Prophets we are, but yet like unto our brethren, (as <hi>Moſes</hi>) Men of God, but yet but men, and ſo ſubject to whatſoever ſins are incident to man's nature as well as others. <hi>Abiathar</hi> here though the <hi>High Priest,</hi> and head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the Church, yet led aſide by ſome corrupt reſpects, goes about (as much as in him lies) to fruſtrate Gods promiſe and appointment. <hi>He helps forward</hi> Adonijah.</p>
            <p>Well, but all this while we have condemned them; how
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65036:13"/> may we now juſtifie God? Was there no partiality, no ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity in him, to prefer the younger before the elder? Primo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniture by his own Law, had the priviledge of a double portion, and doth he now (for no wickedneſs neither that we read of) bar <hi>Adonijah</hi> from this Prerogative? Shall not the Judge of all the world do right? Shall he do any man wrong? that be far from him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Twofold. 1. General. 2. Particular.</p>
            <p>Firſt, God is a free and liberal Agent. He doth and may do whatſoever he will both in Heaven and Earth. His will is the rule of Juſtice; for though ſome will have Juſtice to be the reaſon of his will, (blaſphemouſly enough, if well ſifted) yet 'tis confeſt on all hands, that he wills nothing, but what is juſt. When therefore we hear him clearly enjoyning any thing, we are not (in our weak way) to diſpute the lawfulneſs of it, but with all alacrity to haſten its execution. For God is equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as unable to command, as to commit injuſtice; <hi>All his waies are judgment and truth,</hi> Pſal.—</p>
            <p>The <hi>Canoniſts</hi> affirm of the Pope, <hi>nunquam ligat ſibi manus,</hi> he can never tie his own hands, never limit and reſtrain his own power. They write him down <hi>a God on Earth</hi> and therefore herein they will have him like the <hi>God of Heaven.</hi> And your greateſt Statiſts of Laws in Monarchies, tell us, that they bind only thoſe that are under them. A Coactive power they have not, ſerve only for <hi>Direction</hi> to ſuch as are above them. Beſides, we grant that Laws may be diſpenc'd withal, nay, nullified by the ſame power by which they were made, and that the ground and reaſon of a good Law is alwaies juſtice, though the letter in ſome particular application may be otherwiſe. Hence that uſual Say (conſidering the unſufficiency of Laws, to meet with thoſe millions of circumſtances) (one of which may alter a caſe) <hi>Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a privaete miſchief then a publick inconvenience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Obſervations (ſome of them at leaſt) may not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps (in a Metaphyſical tranſcendent conſideration) utterly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compatible with the Almighty. For we find God (for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent) to have commanded contrary to the letter (to be ſure) of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:65036:13"/> his own Law, As in the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſpoyling the <hi>Egyptians.</hi> Nay in a weightier buſineſſe then the Text holds forth, we find the younger accepted, the Elder rejected. Nay for an Earthly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome too, the point in hand (though attended with other Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances) we find <hi>David</hi> preferred before <hi>Eliab.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, But this Diſcourſe of Gods abſolute power to do whatſoever he will, and that all being truly his both in Heaven and Earth, he may diſpoſe of his own as it pleaſeth him, will perchance ſcarce ſatisfie ſome, and indeed let it be confeſt, ſomething farther, and (I conceive) better may be ſaid to the point.</p>
            <p>Many things are holden in the World by Preſcription, Cuſtome put into the Ballance with Law cleerly out weighs it, and then time out of mind we deem no Title better. Now <hi>Iſraels</hi> caſe was different from that of other Nations. Theſe had been from their very beginnings as <hi>Commoners,</hi> left to the Light of the Law of Nature, and to ſuch Conſtitutions, as they were able to make out from that; But <hi>Iſrael</hi> was Gods Incloſure, continued by his ſpecial particular care under Pupillage as his own peculiar, and the Government amongſt them to the very day of this Conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion went not by Succeſſion but Election, and in that, they were never ſuffer'd to carve out to themſelves, whomſoever they fanci'd as the moſt fit, but as the Power, ſo the continual Exerciſe of it was only in God. From <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Samuel</hi> about five hundred years, they had ſtill rulers, when they had any, of his appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. In all that time (we read not) of a Son ſucceeding his Father, But heaven according to ſeveral Exigencies ſingled them out ſeveral men, of ſeveral Tribes and Families, of proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Abilities, to ſit at the Helm of the State. During the Life of <hi>Samuel,</hi> they require a King like other Nations, but a King ſtill of Gods chooſing, not their own.</p>
            <p>They have <hi>Saul</hi> and he hath a Son both good and valiant, yet he in his Life time perceives the Kingdome deſtined to a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; The Father indeed ſtorms at it. but the Son ſeems well content, and though after both their Deaths, <hi>Abner</hi> ſets another Son of <hi>Sauls</hi> upon the Throne, yet the cauſe thrives not, the whole Kingdome at length devolves unto <hi>David.</hi> So that if
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65036:14"/> 
               <hi>Jonathan</hi> or <hi>Sauls</hi> other Son had no wrong; neither had here <hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nijah;</hi> And if God had not limited himſelf by an after aſſurance to <hi>David,</hi> he might have dealt with him and his poſterity, as he did with <hi>Saul</hi> and his, given the Kingdome to any <hi>Iſraelite;</hi> now however he hath his whole off-ſpring to chooſe in, and might without the leaſt injuſtice have faſtned upon any iſſue of his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well as <hi>Solomon.</hi> So that as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in another caſe, <hi>Huic fit miſericordia, illi non injuria;</hi> God was favourable to <hi>Solomon,</hi> did no injury to <hi>Adonijah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſidering then that the Common-wealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> was ſo conſtituted at the Beginning, and had ſo continued many hundred years, that none could pretend to the Principality by Filiation, and therefore at this time fell not under the Cognizance of that Law of <hi>Primogeniture,</hi> (which God (ſurceaſing his claim) ſuffer'd it to do in the Ages following.) Conſidering too, that as the right of Election was in God, ſo he had continually all along exercis'd the power of it without interruption; for <hi>Joab</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biathar,</hi> boldly to undertake the pointing out of a Supreme Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate without his ſpecial Warrant and Commiſſion, nay to ſet up one when he had appointed another, was a Preſumption worthy the Vengeance inflicted upon them afterwards. For we find (and I thought not fit to conclude without this Note) they paid deerly for it (and ſo ſhall all thoſe ſooner or later that attempt upon any of Gods Reſervations) they had better been out of Employment then have had ſuch Wages. The one loſeth his Life, the other his Office, and Heaven is to be admir'd for the Certainty and Juſtice of its Diſpenſations in both. <hi>Joab</hi> had before commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted divers Murthers, and ſo powerful he was in the State, that Vengeance by the hand of the preſent Magiſtrate durſt not ſeize on him. This Action of his (Springing from the ſame root) pays thoſe old Scores, and as he had ſhed mans blood, ſo by man is his Blood powred forth. <hi>Abiathar</hi> was of the houſe of <hi>Eli,</hi> againſt whom we have Two ſeveral prophetical Denunciations, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> Chap. 2, 3. and this his Stickling for, and Siding with <hi>Adonijah</hi> here, cauſeth his Removal from the Prieſthood; and ſo we ſee thoſe Predictions likewiſe made good by their accompliſhment.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:65036:14"/>
            <p>And this conſideration well ſifted (would the Time, and the Space allotted for this exerciſe bear it) would afford us freſh mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Contemplation and Diſcourſe, about the certain, yet ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ways of Providence.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>How the wiſe Diſpoſer of all things, turns (many times) mans greateſt Shame, into his own greateſt Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>How our very Sins (though Traitors to us their Owners) prove Truſty Executioners of the Almighties purpoſes, and our wickedſt Actions (ſo over-ordered) as they become the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental Examples of Heavens Juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But theſe will fall more fitly into ſome Texts in the Second Chapter.</p>
            <p>To the only wiſe and powerful Trinity, Three perſons, One God, be aſcribed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
